<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Resumos xmlns:xsd="https://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsi="https://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA001</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Are all dental pulp stem cells primed to differentiate into vascular endothelial cells?</Titulo>
		<Autores>Bergamo, MTOP*, Zhang Z, Oliveira TM, Machado MAAM, Nör JE</Autores>
		<Universidade>Odontopediatria, Ortodontia e Saúde Cole - UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - BAURU.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>The purpose of this study was to evaluate if there is a sub-population of dental pulp stem cells that is uniquely primed to differentiate into vascular endothelial cells. Here, we sorted SHED or DPSC according to expression levels of VEGFR1 and exposed them to one of the following conditions: 1) Control medium; 2) Endothelial differentiation medium - Endothelial Growth Medium (EGM) 2-MV supplemented with 50 ng/mL rhVEGF in presence of 0 or 25 &amp;#956;g/ml Bevacizumab. We evaluated cell proliferation and endothelial differentiation potential in vitro through the: Sulforhodamine-B (SRB) assay, Capillary Sprouting Assay, RT-PCR, Western Blot, and Immunofluorescence. We also transplanted VEGFR1-sorted cells into immunodeficient mice and evaluated the impact of VEGFR1 expression levels on microvessel density by histology and immunohistochemistry. We confirmed that dental pulp stem cells differentiate into endothelial cells by increased expression of endothelial cell markers and by capillary sprouting formation upon exposure to endothelial differentiation medium. VEGFR1&lt;sup&gt;low&lt;/sup&gt; dental pulp stem cells proliferated quicker than VEGFR1&lt;sup&gt;high&lt;/sup&gt; cells, indicating their preferential self-renewal. On the other hand, VEGFR1&lt;sup&gt;high&lt;/sup&gt; cells are more prone to vasculogenic differentiation, as they generated more capillary sprouts in vitro and more microvessels in vivo than VEGFR1&lt;sup&gt;low&lt;/sup&gt; cells.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>These data demonstrate that stem cells of the dental pulp have an unique sub-population of cells defined by high VEGFR1 expression that are primed to differentiate into vascular endothelial cells.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPESP N° 2018/13675-0 | NIH/NIDCR  N° RO1-DE021410)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA002</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Central antinociceptive action of Botulinum toxin type A and its effects on the glia-neuron cross-talk in a TMJ-rheumatoid arthritis model</Titulo>
		<Autores>Muñoz-Lora VRM*, Abdalla HB, Matak I, Dugonjic A, Lackovic Z, Clemente-Napimoga JT, Cury AAB</Autores>
		<Universidade>Prótese e Periodontia - FACULDADE DE ODONTOLOGIA DE PIRACICABA.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>We assessed Botulinum toxin type A (BoNT/A) central enzymatic and antinociceptive activity and its possible influence on the glia-neuron communication using a model of antigen-evoked rheumatoid arthritis (RA) in the temporomandibular joint (TMJ) of rats. Wistar rats were induced to RA in the left TMJ by systemic and intra-articular (i.a) challenges using methylated bovine serum albumin. Then, animals were treated with i.a. unilateral (left TMJ) injection of BoNT/A. Spontaneous and mechanically-evoked nocifensive behaviors were assessed by behavioral nocifensive responses, rat grimace scale, and von Frey filaments. Animals were sacrificed and the trigeminal nucleus caudalis (TNC) was collected to perform: 1) immunohistochemical staining of cleaved SNAP25, c-Fos protein and glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP); 2) western blot of microglial P2X7 receptor and CX3 chemokine receptor 1 (CX3CR1); and 3) Elisa of microglial modulators Cathepsin S, Fractalkine and pro-inflammatory cytokines TNF-a and IL-1b. BoNT/A application was associated with the appearance of truncated SNAP-25 in the sensory TNC. BoNT/A reduced spontaneous and evoked nociceptive behaviors, bilateral c-Fos expression, and markers of neuronal and glial activation.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>The antinociceptive activity of BoNT/A is associated with its ability to transport to upper sensory regions and reduce neuronal and glial cells activation. BoNT/A might be useful as a central acting and neuromodulatory drug for chronic pain conditions. However, BoNT/A effects on glial cells should be carefully explored.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPs - FAPESP N° 2017/07741-7 | FAPs - BEPE-FAPESP N° 2018/13575-5 | CAPES N° 001)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA003</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Impact of biomineralization on resin/demineralized dentin bond longevity in a minimally invasive approach: an &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; 18-month follow-up</Titulo>
		<Autores>Moreira KMS*, Bertassoni LEB, Davies RPW, Joia F, Höfling JF, Nascimento FD, Puppin-Rontani RM</Autores>
		<Universidade>Odontologia Infantil - FACULDADE DE ODONTOLOGIA DE PIRACICABA.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>This study determined the impact of 0.2% NaF-NaF, casein phosphopeptide-amorphous calcium phosphate-CPP-ACP, or P&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;-4 peptide on resin/dentin demineralized (DD) interface longevity. DD provided by biological method, used 255 caries-free third molars, randomly distributed into 5 groups: Sound dentin-SD; DD; DD+NaF-NaF; DD+CPP-ACP-CPP-ACP; DD+P&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;-4-P&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;-4. A block of Filtek&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt; Z350 composite resin (4mm/height) was bonded with Adper&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt; Single Bond 2 over dentin surfaces. The resin/dentin blocks stored in Simulated Body Fluid/37&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;C under modified simulated pulpal pressure were tested by µTBS, nanoinfiltration, in situ zymography and µ-CT, at 24-h, 6 and 18-mo. Data from µTBS and µ-CT were submitted to ANOVA and Tukey tests, and from failure patterns and in situ zymography to Kruskal-Wallis test (&amp;#945;=5%). Descriptive analysis was performed for nanoinfiltration and hybrid layer formation/degradation. The highest µ-CT values were showed by CPP-ACP (p&lt;0.01) and P11-4 (p&lt;0.01) groups, over time; NaF showed similar values than DD (p&gt;0.05), whereas CPP-ACP resembled the SD (p&gt;0.05), over time; P11-4 reached values close to SD, at 24-h and 18-mo (p&gt;0.05); DD and NaF showed highest adhesive failure all periods (p&lt;0.05). SD, CPP-ACP and P11-4 presented the lowest nanoinfiltration and proteolytic activity, at the 24h and increased after 6 and 18-mo. The mineral density increased in the DD for CPP-ACP and P11-4 groups (p&lt;0.05).</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Therefore, CPP-ACP and P&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;-4 showed to be a promising method for treating DD, increasing the longevity of adhesive restorations.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio></Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA004</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Proteomic profile of the acquired enamel pellicle of children with early childhood caries and caries-free children</Titulo>
		<Autores>Silva NC*, Oliveira BP, Ventura TMO, Toniolo J, Buzalaf MAR, Rodrigues JA</Autores>
		<Universidade>UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DO RIO GRANDE DO SUL.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>Early Childhood Caries (ECC) is defined as the presence of one or more primary teeth with carious lesion on some surface, in children up to 6 years old. The acquired enamel pellicle (AEP) play an important role in the pathogenesis of ECC, working as a protective interface between the tooth surface and the oral cavity. There is no data on the proteomic profile of AEP from children with ECC. The objective of this study was to compare the proteomic profile of the in vivo AEP from children, aged 3 to 5 years old, with ECC (n=10) and caries-free (CF; n=10). After AEP samples have been collected, they were processed by proteomic analysis (nLC-ESI-MS/MS). For the label-free quantitative analysis the PLGS Software was used. In total, 241 proteins were identified. Among the exclusive proteins, basic salivary proline-rich protein (PRP) 1 and 2, cystatin-B and cystatin-SA were found only in CF and should be highlighted. When comparing ECC and CF, decreased proteins in the CF included 6 hemoglobin isoforms, serum albumin, neutrophil defensin 3 and proteins S100-A8 and A9, and increased proteins included submaxillary gland androgen-regulated protein 3B, histatin-1, statherin, 3 isoforms of PRP and alpha-amylase 1 and 2B.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>These findings show that there are differences in the protein profile of AEP when compared ECC with CF children. The exclusive and the increased proteins found in CF group might have protective functions that play a role in the prevention to caries, besides provide important insights for the development of new therapeutic strategies and development of dental products for ECC.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CNPq N° 314532/2018-8)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA005</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Upper airway changes in miniscrew-anchored maxillary protraction with hybrid and hyrax expanders: a randomized clinical trial</Titulo>
		<Autores>Miranda F*, Pugliese FS, Massaro C, Bastos JCC, Santos AM, Janson G, Palomo JM, Garib DG</Autores>
		<Universidade>Odontopediatria, Ortodontia e Sc - UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - BAURU.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>The aim of this study was to compare the upper airway space changes after miniscrew-anchored maxillary protraction with hybrid and conventional hyrax expanders. The sample comprised 40 Class III malocclusion growing patients that were randomized into two groups of miniscrew-anchored maxillary protraction. The group HH was treated a hybrid hyrax appliance in the maxilla and two miniscrews distally to the canines in the mandible. Class III elastics were used from the maxillary first molar to the mandibular miniscrews until anterior crossbite correction. The group CH was treated with a similar protocol except for the conventional hyrax expander in the maxilla. CBCT was obtained before (T1) and after 12 months of therapy (T2). The shape and size of upper airway were assessed. Intergroup comparisons were performed using t tests (P&lt;0.05). The group HH was composed by 13 patients (6 female, 7 male) with a mean age of 10.42 years. The group CH was composed by 15 patients (5 female, 7 male) with a mean age of 11.38 years. Good reproducibility was found for all measurements. Anteroposterior and transverse increases of the upper airway were found for both groups. The oropharynx and the most constricted area increased similarly in both groups.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Maxillary protraction using miniscrews as anchorage produced an increase in the upper airways. No differences in upper airway changes were observed using protraction anchored on hybrid or conventional hyrax expanders.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPs - FAPESP N° 2017/04141-9  | FAPs - FAPESP N° 2017/24115-2 | FAPs - FAPESP N° 2019/03175-2)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA006</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Maxillary dentoskeletal outcomes of the expander with the differential opening and the fan-type expander: a randomized clinical trial</Titulo>
		<Autores>Massaro C*, Ruellas ACO, Cevidanes LHS, Yatabe MS, Janson G, Miranda F, Lauris JRP, Garib DG</Autores>
		<Universidade>Ortodontia - UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - BAURU.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Autodeclarado "&lt;em&gt;Patente referente ao expansor com abertura diferencial no nome da autora Daniela Gamba Garib (PI 1101050-9, Instituto nacional de patente e indústria-Brasil).&lt;/em&gt;"</Conflito>
		<Resumo>The aim of this randomized clinical trial was to compare the maxillary expander with differential opening (EDO) and the fan-type expander (FE) in the mixed dentition by means of cone-beam computed tomography (CBCT) three-dimensional models superimposed on the cranial base. Forty-eight patients with maxillary dental arch constriction were randomly allocated into 2 study groups. Group EDO was composed of 24 patients (mean age of 7.62 years) treated with the EDO. Group FE comprised 24 patients (mean age of 7.83 years) treated with the FE. CBCT scans were acquired before and after rapid maxillary expansion. Three-dimensional dentoskeletal changes were assessed after cranial base superimposition using the software ITK-SNAP and 3D Slicer. T or Mann-Whitney U tests with Holm-Bonferroni correction were used for intergroup comparisons (P&lt;0.05). Maxillary lateral displacements were greater in the EDO group, while the vertical and anteroposterior changes were similar in both groups. The increase in the intercanine distance and the canine buccal inclination were slightly greater in the FE group, while the intermolar changes and the molar buccal inclination were greater in the EDO group.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>The expander with differential opening (EDO) produced a greater transversal skeletal expansion compared to the fan-type expander (FE), with similar vertical and anteroposterior effects. Dental changes were greater in the molar region for patients treated with EDO and in the canine region for patients treated with FE.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CAPES | FAPs - FAPESP N° 2017/12911-9 | NIDCR R01 DE024450)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA007</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Nanoscale biomimetic mineralization of bioprinted gelatin methacryloyl for tissue engineering</Titulo>
		<Autores>Balbinot GS*, Subbiah R, Athirasala A, Collares FM, Bertassoni LEB</Autores>
		<Universidade>Odontologia Conservadora - UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DO RIO GRANDE DO SUL.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>Mimicking the complex structure of bone tissue is key for effective bone regeneration. This study aimed to develop a unique process to 3D bioprint microscale cell-laden scaffolds that mimick the bone nanoscale structure and function with precision and can be delivered via injection for minimally invasive regenerative procedures. Gelatin methacryloyl (GelMA) hydrogels were produced by stereolithography and used as an organic substrate for biomimetic nanoscale mineralization via a proprietary protein-mediated biomimetic mineralization process with osteopontin in a Ca&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3-&lt;/sup&gt; supersaturated media. Mineralization was optimized for different media, gelMA concentrations, and cross-linking times. The mineral content and mechanical properties were evaluated, and optimized hydrogels were used for dental pulp stem cells (DPSCs) encapsulation. The printability was tested for injectable mineralized microgels production. After the screening, 10wt% gelMA printed for 25s and mineralized in &amp;#945;-MEM was chosen, reaching an elastic modulus of 123.94kPa. Mineralized hydrogels DPSCs viability and differentiation. Injectable flower-shaped microgels (900µm) were successfully printed and mineralized.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>The nanoscale mineralization of bone-like cell-laden bioprinted microgels was demonstrated for the first time. The obtained nanostructure evidence the ability of these materials to mimic the intra- and extracellular environments of bone. Mineralized microgels were successfully produced for injectable minimally invasive regenerative procedures.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio></Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA008</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Color stability in relation to degree of conversion and monomer elution for different commercial composites</Titulo>
		<Autores>Cardoso LI*, Collares FM, Spohr AM, Mota EG, Burnett Júnior LH</Autores>
		<Universidade>Clínico - PONTIFÍCIA UNIVERSIDADE CATÓLICA DO RIO GRANDE DO SUL.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>This study aimed to evaluate the color stability (&amp;#8710;E) of three commercial brands of composite resins when immersed in distilled water, within 24 hours, 30 days and 180 days, as well as the degree of monomer conversion and BisGMA component release. Five specimens of each resin shade were made for color stability evaluation (Easyshade 4.0, Vita) and three specimens for the degree of monomer conversion evaluation (FTIR). Each increment of resin in the specimens was light-cured for 20s using a polywave LED and these were then stored in distilled water at 37°C after photoactivation. A color scale pattern was made from the material studied, following the Vita (Vita) scale, to determine a standard of comparison. The elution of BisGMA was analyzed by liquid chromatography with mass spectrometer. The three-way ANOVA test allowed us to observe that the interaction between time/shade/brand was significant (p = 0.0001), with all the studied resins showing color changes in relation to the pattern in the studied periods. Empress Direct was the only one to display &amp;#8710;E&amp;#8805;2.7over the 180 days on shades B1 and A1, and there was no significant correlation between degree of conversion, &amp;#8710;E and BisGMA elution. There was a significant direct correlation between degree of conversion and &amp;#8710;E in 30 days and inverse in 180 days.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Thus, it is suggested that there is a stabilization of the resinous material after 30 days and thus, a balance of its optical properties.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CAPES)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA009</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Effect of different surface treatments and glaze application on the wear resistance of a stained hybrid ceramic</Titulo>
		<Autores>Tribst JPM*, Dal-Piva AMO, Anami LC, Kleverlaan CJ, Bottino MA</Autores>
		<Universidade>Materiais Odontológicos e Prótese - INSTITUTO DE CIÊNCIA E TECNOLOGIA / ICT-UNESP-SJC.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>To evaluate the effect of surface treatment and glaze application on the external staining wear resistance of a hybrid ceramic. Thirty-two (32) specimens (14 x 10 x 3 mm) were glued to a wheel device and divided into 8 groups according to the surface treatment prior to the staining (polishing: Pol, acid etching: Ac, sandblasting: Sd, or self-etching silane: Ses) and glaze application (with: gl or without: -gl). After the wear test on the ACTA wear machine, the staining wear rate was determined during seven intervals of 20,000 cycles, using a profilometer. The three-body wear rates were analyzed using three-way ANOVA and post-hoc Tukey test, all with &amp;#945;=5%. Scanning Electron Microscopy (SEM) analysis was performed to access the surface wear profile. The three-body wear rates were affected by surface treatment*glaze application*number of cycles interaction (p &lt; 0.001). 100% of the staining was removed at 20,000 for Pol, at 40,000 for Pol+gl, at 60,000 for Ses+gl, at 80,000 for Ac, at 100,000 for Sd and Ses, at 120,000 for Ac+gl and at 140,000 for Sd+gl. SEM showed similar worn surface profiles for the tested groups and the glaze removal occurred after 140,000 cycles.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>The sandblasting followed by glaze application as surface treatment showed more suitable capability to maintain the external staining on hybrid ceramic surface. The glaze application did not protect the stain regardless the ceramic surface treatment performed.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPs - FAPESP N° 18/07404-3)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA010</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Changes in zirconia surface architecture and evaluation of shear bond strength with veneering ceramic after plasma treatment</Titulo>
		<Autores>Bitencourt SB*, Santos DM, Bastos NA, Bonfante EA, Rangel EC, Pesqueira AA</Autores>
		<Universidade>Materiais Odontológicos e Prótese - UNIVERSIDADE ESTADUAL PAULISTA - ARAÇATUBA.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>To characterize the zirconia (Y-TZP) surface submitted to different surface treatments (with and without plasma associations) and to evaluate the shear bond strength (SBS) with the veneering ceramic (VC) after different aging periods. 301 Y-TZP specimens were fabricated and distributed into 7 groups (n=43): C (control): no treatment; Al: airborne abrasion with 27 µm Al2O3 particle; L: liner; P: plasma; Al+L: airborne abrasion + liner; Al+P: airborne abrasion + plasma; P+L: plasma + liner. The Y-TZP surface was characterized by SEM, EDS, AFM, roughness, and surface-free energy (SFE). XRD was used to verify the crystal structure after each surface treatment performed. SBS between Y-TZP and the VC was verified after three aging protocols: initial and after hydrothermal aging (autoclave for 5h) and thermal fatigue (30,000 baths - 5-55°C). One- (roughness and SFE) and two-way ANOVA (SBS), and Tukey's HSD test were used as a statistical analysis. For the plasma groups, a homogeneous and full surface coverage was observed on SEM and AFM, with globular formation. Peaks of Si were found for Al, L, Al+L, and P+L groups. Roughness was lower for groups C, P, and Al+P. For SFE, the highest values were found when the liner was applied. The higher monoclinic content was found for Al+L and Al+P. For the initial and after thermal fatigue, the P group presented the highest SBS values.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Plasma treatment itself or associated with liner was capable to deposit a film on the zirconia surface without altering its structure and to improve the SBS with VC, even after aging.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPs - FAPESP N° 2017/13933-6 | FAPs - FAPESP N° 2018/24984-3)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA011</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Objective assessment of the combined effect of exomass-related and motion artefacts in Cone beam CT</Titulo>
		<Autores>Candemil A P*, Oliveira ML, Freitas DQ, Haiter Neto F, Wenzel A, Spin Neto R</Autores>
		<Universidade>Diagnóstico Oral - FACULDADE DE ODONTOLOGIA DE PIRACICABA.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>The aim of this study was to assess the combined effect of cone-beam computed tomography (CBCT) exomass-related and patient motion artefacts. A cylindrical phantom containing 21 tubes filled with a radiopaque solution, allowing the inclusion of three titanium implants in the periphery to induce exomass-related artefacts, was mounted on a robot simulating 0.75-, 1.50-, and 3-mm movements (nodding/lateral rotation/tremor). CBCT images with/without exomass and with/without movements were acquired, in duplicate, in three units. Voxel value mean and standard deviation were assessed from each tube. For each CBCT volume, the 21 mean voxel values were averaged providing the overall mean voxel value (OMVV), and the standard deviation was calculated providing overall voxel value inhomogeneity (OVVI). The standard deviation from each of the 21 volumes-of-interest were averaged, providing overall image noise (ON). OMVV, OVVI, and ON were averaged for the duplicate acquisitions. The effect of the diverse tested conditions was inferred from a repeated-measures analysis of variance, followed by Sidak's test (&amp;#945;=0.05). Images acquired with exomass had lower OMVV, and higher OVVI and ON. Movement artefacts aggravated exomass-related alterations. OMVV and OVVI were mostly affected by 3-mm nodding movements. Motion-artefact correction was effective.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>In conclusion, CBCT images are altered by exomass-related artefacts, and this finding is aggravated in the presence of motion artefacts. Motion-artefact correction eliminated the impact of movement.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CAPES N° 001 | Pró-Reitoria de Pós-Graduação at UNICAMP N° 11/2019)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA012</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Automated Identification of Dental Implants by Using Artificial Intelligence</Titulo>
		<Autores>Santos RPM*, Oliveira GAA, Aranha-Neto IS, Silva AIV, Alves TKC, Carmelo JC, Manzi FR</Autores>
		<Universidade>Odontologia - PONTIFÍCIA UNIVERSIDADE CATÓLICA DE MINAS GERAIS.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>The aim of this study was to develop and evaluate accuracy of a computer assisted system based on Artificial Intelligence (AI) for detecting and identifying automatically Dental Implants(DI) brands using digital periapical radiographs.A total amount of 1800 digital periapical radiographs with DI from three distinct manufacturers (f1,f2,f3) f1=600, f2=600 and f3=600 was split into training dataset (n = 1440 [80%]) and testing dataset (n = 360 [20%]) groups. The images were evaluated by a software developed through Convolutional Neural Networks (CNN) aimed to identify the manufacturer of IDs contained therein. Accuracy, Sensitivity, Specificity, positive and negative predictive values, and ROC curve were calculated for detection and diagnostic performance of CNN algorithm. At the final epoch (25), it was obtained 99.78% of system accuracy for training data, 99.36% for testing data and 85.29% for validation data. The latest one corresponds to the actual accuracy of dental implant manufacturer identification contained in digital periapical radiographs after the system learning process.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>The results obtained in this study show that Deep CNN algorithm provides high accuracy for identifying dental implants by means of digital periapical radiographs, being a useful tool in odontological practice. With a more comprehensive data bank, this system may be widely used helping dentists to work with more predictability and to eliminate the challenge of discovering the implant model installed in patients when there is no previous treatment information.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio></Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA013</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Phenotypic characterization of macrophages during induced apical periodontitis in mice</Titulo>
		<Autores>Pucinelli CM*, Nelson-Filho P, León JE, Faccioli LH, Sorgi CA, Silva LAB, Segato RAB</Autores>
		<Universidade>Clínica Infantil - UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - RIBEIRÃO PRETO.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>The aim was to describe the M1 and M2 macrophages characterization by biomarker expression during the apical periodontitis (AP) formation. 130 wild-type mice were divided into control (sound teeth; n=50) and experimental (teeth with AP; n=80) groups. After 5 experimental periods, all animals were euthanized and the specimens submitted to histotechnical process in order to describe the apical and periapical tissue characteristics under conventional microscopy. Also, under fluorescence microscopy, morphometry was performed to measure the AP area. Were performed qRT-PCR for Cxcl10, CxCL9, iNos2, Arg1, Ym1, Fizz1 and MRC1 and Luminex® assay for GM-CSF, IFN-&amp;#947;, IL-4, IL-13, IL-10, IL-6, IL-1&amp;#946; and TNF-&amp;#945;. ANOVA test and Tukey post-test were performed for morphometry. For qRT-PCR and Luminex®, Kruskal-Wallis test and Dunn post-test were performed. It was used GraphPad Prism 7.0a software (&amp;#945;=5%). The results showed a dynamically progression of AP, with a progressive destruction of the periodontal ligament, cement and alveolar bone. Markers for both, M1 and M2 macrophages, were present at different levels throughout the experimental periods, suggesting the occurrence of compensatory pathways.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>In conclusion both macrophages were detected at different levels during all periods. It was observed a predominance of M1 phenotype in the early periods and M2 phenotype at 14 and 21 days, but returning to the M1 phenotype when the lesion was established.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: Fapesp N° 2016/24900-9 | CAPES N° 88881.190601/2018-01 | CNPq N° 140139/2019-2)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA014</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Epigenetic regulation in human periodontal ligament cells with distinct osteogenic potential: Genome-Wide analysis</Titulo>
		<Autores>Assis RIF*, Racca F, Ferreira RS, Nociti-Júnior FH, Ruiz KGS, Silva RA, Wiench M, Andia DC</Autores>
		<Universidade>Periodontia e Protese - FACULDADE DE ODONTOLOGIA DE PIRACICABA.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>Human periodontal ligament cells (PDLCs) can show distinct osteogenic potential, limiting their clinical applications. Through genomic approaches, our goal is to identify markers to assess osteogenic potential. PDLCs with high (h-) and low (l-) osteogenic potential were cultivated in control medium or osteogenic medium for 10 days, in vitro. DNA, chromatin and RNA were submitted to methylome, Assay for transposase accessible chromatin (ATAC) and RNA protocols, followed by next generation sequencing and bioinformatics analysis. After middle osteogenesis, results showed more differentially methylated probes (hyper/hypo) in l-PDLCs than in h- (74 x 41) with common methylated regions at gene body. There were more regions with accessible chromatin in the l-PDLCs, mainly in genes related to osteogenesis (RUNX2 l-43 x h-8; SP7 l-5 x h-1), transcription factors (Gli l-70 x h-17, Rab23) and pluripotency (OCT4 l-4 x h-0). The regulatory regions associated with cell identity (superenhancers) activated in l- were distinct from h-PDLCs. RNA-seq confirmed a different transcriptional pattern.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>We unravel the epigenetic and transcriptional patterns of PDLCs with distinct osteogenic potential, showing distinct epigenetic regulation and transcriptional background, and this could affect gene markers and therefore, the clinical application outcome.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPs - FAPESP  N° 2019/01727-8 | FAPs - FAPESP  N° 2017/12158-9 | FAPs - FAPESP  N° 2017/07944-5)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA015</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Interactions between hemodialysis vintage with xerostomia and tooth loss on oral health-related quality of life</Titulo>
		<Autores>Oliveira LM*, Schöffer C, Santi SS, Antoniazzi RP, Zanatta FB</Autores>
		<Universidade>Estomatologia - UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DE SANTA MARIA.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>The aim of the present cross-sectional study was to evaluate whether tooth loss and xerostomia are independently associated with oral health-related quality of life (OHRQoL) in individuals with end-stage renal disease (ESRD) and whether hemodialysis vintage (HV) modifies the effect of these associations. One hundred eighty adults with ESRD were assessed by calibrated examiners. Oral examinations were performed for untreated dental caries, periodontitis, tooth loss (&amp;#8804; 8 or &gt; 8 teeth) and xerostomia (absent or present). HV was determined using hospital records and categorized as &amp;#8804; 12, 13-72 or &amp;#8805; 73 months. OHRQoL was assessed using the simplified version of the Oral Health Impact Profile (OHIP14) questionnaire. Adjusted multivariate negative binomial regression analysis was used to calculate the rate ratio (RR) of OHIP14 scores according to the exposures of interest and interactions with HV. In the adjusted model, xerostomia and tooth loss were significantly associated with poorer OHRQoL. Moreover, longer HV (&amp;#8805; 73 months) negatively modified the effect of the associations between the exposures [xerostomia (RR = 2.96; 95% CI: 1.48 to 5.90); tooth loss (RR = 4.13; 95% CI: 2.00 to 8.51)] and outcome.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Xerostomia and tooth loss exert an influence on OHRQoL in individuals with end-stage renal disease, with a greater impact found among those on hemodialysis for a longer period of time. Policy makers should consider the greater impact of oral conditions on OHRQoL in extended HV by giving additional priority to patients on long-term pretransplant hemodialysis.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CAPES N° 001)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA016</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Analysis of the oral biofilm diversity and protein profile of saliva and acquired enamel pellicle of individuals with periodontitis</Titulo>
		<Autores>Amado PPP*, Kawamoto D, Saraiva L, Siqueira WL, Mayer MPA</Autores>
		<Universidade>Microbiologia - UNIVERSIDADE  DE SÃO PAULO.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>The etiology of Grade C/molar-incisor pattern periodontitis (GC/MIP), Localized Aggressive Periodontits, is poorly understood. We determinate the oral and gut microbiomes, inflammatory mediators and whole saliva (WS) and acquired enamel pellicle (AEP) proteomes of Afro-descendants with GC/MIP and their age/race/gender-matched non-affected controls (n=7). Biofilms from supra/subgingival sites (OB) and feces were analyzed by &lt;em&gt;16S rRNA &lt;/em&gt;sequencing. WS and AEP proteomes were determined by LC-ESI-MS/MS. Cytokines/chemokines WS and WS proteolytic activity were evaluated. GC/MIP supragingival biofilm presented greater abundance of opportunistic bacteria. &lt;em&gt;Synergistetes&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Spirochaetae&lt;/em&gt; were increased whereas &lt;em&gt;Actinobacteria&lt;/em&gt; was reduced in GC/MIP OB compared to controls. GC/MIP oral microbiome presented reduction in commensals and enrichment in &lt;em&gt;A. actinomycetemcomitans&lt;/em&gt; and sulfidogenic bacteria (SB). SB was more abundant in fecal microbiome of GC/MIP. Increase of CCL2/CCL25 and decrease of CCL17/CCL27 were observed in GC/MIP. AEP proteins such as ALMS1 and Cystatin-S, and WS proteins such as alpha-enolase, profilin-1, dystonin, A2ML1, alpha-actinin-4 and IGHA1 were differentially detected in the studied groups. WS proteolytic activity was more pronounced in GC/MIP than in controls.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Dysbiosis in GC/MIP is not restricted to periodontitis sites, suggesting that antimicrobial therapies should address the whole mouth and the gut. WS and AEP proteins, and chemokines have potential to be used as biomarkers of GC/MIP.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPESP N° 2015/00259-0)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA017</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Effect of topical PTH 1-34 added to bioglass on peri-implant defect in orchiectomized rats</Titulo>
		<Autores>Gomes-Ferreira PHS*, Micheletti C, Frigério PB, Monteiro NG, De-Souza-batista FR, Lisboa Filho PN, Grandfield K, Okamoto R</Autores>
		<Universidade>Cirurgia e Clínica Integrada - UNIVERSIDADE ESTADUAL PAULISTA - ARAÇATUBA.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>The objective of this work was to evaluate a bioglass functionalized with parathyroid hormone (PTH 1-34) using the sonochemistry technique in peri-implant defects in orchiectomized rats. 96 rats were divided into two groups, i.e. SHAM - control surgery and ORQ - orchiectomy. Each group was subdivided into three sub-groups: CLOT (pre-implant defect, without bioglass); BG (pre-implant defect and bioglass); BGPTH (pre-implant defect and bioglass functionalized with topical PTH 1-34). Each animal received an implant in the tibial metaphysis. Euthanasia occurred at 30 and 60 days after implant placement. MicroCT, laser confocal microscopy, biomechanics, immunohistochemistry, PCR-RT, and electron microscopyanalyses (energy dispersive x-ray spectroscopy, scanning electron microscopy and transmission electron microscopy (TEM)) were performed. As suggested by microtomographic parameters, biomaterial with or without PTH 1-34 showed improvement in bone repair. Analysis of fluorochromes and biomechanics indicated that the functionalized biomaterial increased bone regeneration in the ORQ group to the same level as the SHAM group without PTH 1-34. Immunohistochemistry and PCR analyses show positive changes in groups with PTH 1-34. Nanoscale imaging with TEM suggested the presence of a greater dissolution area of the bioglass and greater organization of collagen fibers in the ORQ BGPTH group.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Overall, the functionalization of bioglass with PTH 1-34 showed improvement in bone regeneration and resulted to be even more effective in the osteoporotic animals.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: FAPs - FAPESP N° 2017/08187-3)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA018</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Stress distribution and micro-gap formation at the abutment-implant interface: a three-dimensional finite element analysis</Titulo>
		<Autores>Tonin BSH*, He Y, Ye N, Chew HP, Fok A</Autores>
		<Universidade>Materiais Dentários e Prótese - UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - RIBEIRÃO PRETO.</Universidade>
		<Conflito>Não há conflito de interesse</Conflito>
		<Resumo>This study aims to investigate the stress distribution in the prosthetic screw and the formation of micro-gaps at the implant-abutment interface of conical connections with titanium (Ti) and yttrium-stabilized zirconium (Y-TZP) abutments. Three-dimensional finite models of the above implant-abutment connections were created. The analyses were conducted using a screw torque of 20 N.cm and an oblique load at 30º from 10 to 100 N at intervals of 10 N, and from 120 to 280 N at intervals of 20 N. The stress distribution, the micro-gap formation process, and the critical load for bridging of the internal implant space, and the size of the micro-gaps were evaluated. The models showed similar patterns of von Mises stress which was mainly concentrated at the top and in the middle of the screw. For all the models, the implant-abutment contact area decreased with increasing load. Above 140 N, bridging of the internal implant space was found when over 70% of the interfacial area was opened. Under 280 N, more than 90% of the interface had a gap larger than 30 mm.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Overall, this study does not indicate any obvious advantage of Ti or Y-TZP abutments over each other. Although the simulated micro-gaps and bridging of the internal implant space can explain the presence of bacteria detected clinically inside implants, the relationship between bacterial invasion and micro-gaps needs further research.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>&lt;em&gt;(Apoio: CAPES N° 88881-187982/2018-01)&lt;/em&gt;</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
</Resumos>
